Alright now! You all fresh niggers,
you'all gonna be in the cutting game.
Very simple! I want you to take your knife,
yank 'em cane, make 'em sing.
Take the cane off.
Cut my tops, clean the stalks off.
Throw it on the pile for replanting again.
Now them cane ain't gonna jump up and bite you,
don't shy 'bout it.
Rushy boys, rushy!
Alright, alright, alright.
Thank you for the music.
Come on.
Get in there, boy.
Give me a kiss.
- I love you. - I love you too, dad.
Sleep well.
I'll take this.
I don't wanna hear any more noise.
Good night.
Three weeks and two days.
It is the custom.
I wonder what you'll do without me?
I won't stay idle.
Darling, it's good money.
If only I didn't have to share your cooking with other people.
You don't.
Come on.
Be good for your mother.
Ok, Alonzo?
Can I get a kiss, please? Thank you.
- Travel safely, love. - Stay safely.
Ready.
- Good day, Mr. Northup. - Good day.
Call the devil's name. There he is now.
Mr. Northup,
I have two gentlemen acquaintance you should make.
Misters Brown and Hamilton.
Sir.
Mr. Northup, these two gentlemen
were inquiring about distinguished individuals,
and I was just this very moment saying Solomon Northup
- is an expert player on the violin. - He was indeed.
Mr. Moon is being overly gracious.
Taking into consideration his graciousness and your modesty,
may we trouble you for a moment of your time to converse, sir?
Of course.
Sir.
- A circus? - That is our usual employee.
The company currently in the city of Washington.
Circus too constricting a word to describe
the talented and merry band with which we travel.
It is a spectacle unlike most have ever witnessed.
Creatures from the darkest Africa as yet unseen by civilized man.
Acrobats from the Orient
who contort themselves in the most confounding manners.
And I myself in aide of Mr. Brown,
an internationally renowned practitioner
in the art of prestidigitation.
We are on our way thither to rejoin the company,
having left for a short time
to make a small profit from our own exhibitions.
The reason for our inquiry with Mr. Moon...
Yes. We had just a devil of a time
in procuring music for our entertainments.
Men of true talents are seemingly in short supply.
Thank you, sir.
If we could persuade you to accompany us as far as Washington,
we could give you one dollar for each day's services
and three dollars for every night played at our performances.
In addition, we would provide sufficient pay,
for your return here to Saratoga,
two weeks from today.
Welcome to Washington, Solomon.
Good Day.
- I'm telling you it's too much. - Some say not enough.
Solomon.
Forty-three dollars. All to you.
That it's far more than my wages amount to.
- To our most profitable week. - Cheers!
- Cheers! - Cheers!
Another.
Gentlemen, your generosity
- is extraordinary. - And your talents are undeniable.
- To Solomon! - Cheers.
Cheers.
That's all right, Solomon.
No shame in it. No shame at all.
Hamilton, we must hurry.
One too many libations, have we there?
I'm so sorry.
We won't hear it. We won't.
Let him sleep, Hamilton.
A good night's rest.
And tomorrow...
Tomorrow you will feel as well and refreshed..
as if the earth were new again.
Hamilton! There's nothing more we can do for him.
Such is the pity.
Well, boy, how yah feel now?
My name...
My name is Solomon Northup.
I am a free man.
a resident of Saratoga, New York.
The residence of my wife and children who are equally free.
and you have no right whatsoever to detain me--
- Yah not any free man . - And I promise you,
I promise you upon my liberation
I will have satisfaction for this wrong.
Resolve this. Produce your papers.
Yah no free man.
And yah ain't from Saratoga.
Yah from Georgia.
Yah ain't a free man.
Yah nuthin' but a Georgia runaway.
Yah a just a..
runaway nigger from Georgia.
You're a slave!
Yah a Georgia slave!
Are yah a slave?
No.
Help!
Help me!
Somebody help me!
Help!
That old thing of yours is just rags and tatters.
You need something proper to wear.
Go'on. Put it on.
There.
That's fine.
Got no gratitude?
- No! It was from my wife. - Rags and tatters.
Rags and tatters.
Go on. Warsh up.
The boy, too. Get him clean.
Scrub now.
Do you know when my mama will come?
- Hush him up! - Mama! Mama!
- Quiet! Quiet. Quiet! - Mama!
- Hush him up! - Mama!
Your mother will come, I swear she will,
but you must be silent.
Be silent!
We need a sympathetic ear.
An opportunity to explain our situation--
Who in your estimation is that sympathetic ear?
The two men I journeyed with.
I'm certain they're making inquires at this very moment.
I would be just as certain they are counting the money
paid for delivering you to this place.
They were not kidnappers. They were artists.
- Fellow performers. - You know that?
You know for certain who they were?
The reality to come is us being transported southward.
New Orleans if I was to venture.
After we arrive, we'll be put to market.
And beyond that...
well, I suppose once in a slave state there's only one outcome.
No.
I don't say that to give you empty agitation, John...
For y'all. For y'all they ain't nothin' but that!
But John was'n kidnapped.
John is bein' hold as debt, tha's all.
Massa pay his debt, and John be redeemed--
Boy, our masters will not come for us.
John... John's sorry for y'all, but tha's how it be.
Where y'all goin', yah goin' witout John.
- Mama! - Randall.
Mama!
Are you alright?
Come on, get up!
- I said get up! - No, no, don't...
Now, I don't want to hear yer talk. Get in the yard.
- No, I'm not sure... - Ain't no need for all that.
Just take a little trip, that's all.
Don't want to frighten the children
over a little boat ride, do yah?
John's massa gunna pay his debt.
His massa gunna pay his debt.
I don't want to hear a word, out of none a yah.
Not a one.
No!
All right, come on.
Come on!
Come on, child, come on.
Follw your mom.
- Come on, boy. - Come on.
Come on, move it!
Let's go! Come on! Up, upstairs.
Hit it!
Come on, let's go.
Get up there, kid!
Come on, move it!
- All right, come on! - Move it, boy!
Take him down!
Hey, you! Come on, get up!
Get down, right there.
Come on.
Right there. Sit down.
Cheer up and don't be so cast down.
If you want to survive, do and say as little as possible.
Tell no one who you really are,
and tell no one you can read and write.
Unless you want to be a dead nigger.
Now, keep your mouth shut.
I say we fight.
The crew is fairly small.
If it were well planned,
I believe they could be strong armed.
Three can't go against a whole crew?
The rest here are niggers,
born and bred slaves. Niggers ain't got no stomach for a fight.
- Not a damn one. - All I know,
we get where we're travelling, we'll wish we'd died right here.
Survival is not about certain death,
it is about keeping your head down.
Days ago I was with my family,
in my home.
Now you tell me all is lost.
Tell no one who I am? That's the way to survive.
Well, I don't want to survive.
I want to live.
It's better off. Better than us.
I don't see him. Clemens!
Clemens Ray!
- Clemens! - Master Ray, sir!
- Who's in charge here? - I'm the captain!
I am Mr. Jonas Ray.
My solicitor has documentation verifying
that the Negro known as Clemens Ray is my property.
I know nothing of this arrangement.
You are ordered to return that property immediately
or be charged with thievery.
Free him!
Master!
Clemens! Clemens!
- Get back! Get him back! - Clemens!
Clemens!
Mr. Parker?
Oh, Mr. Northup.
Mrs. Northup,
Solomon, can I interest you with a new cravat?
Pure silk by way of the French.
We are in need of a fresh carry all for my Mrs's travels.
Nothing more.
A year's passed already? Off towards Sandy Hill again?
- Yes , I am. - I have just the thing.
Something to suit your style,
and yet sturdy enough for the forty miles round trip.
- It's beautiful. - But at what price?
We will take it.
Children, come see what your father has just purchased for me.
One moment, sir, and you will be assisted.
- Mr. Parker? - Sir?
If we can discuss the price...
Forgive me, Solomon, Mrs. Northup.
A customer waits.
Welcome, sir.
Shop well sir, but mind your wallet.
- Pay no attention to this gentleman's nonsense. - Jasper!
My regrets for the intrusion, sir.
No intrusion.
- Good day, sir. - Good day.
Jasper, out!
Very good.
Let's see here... Eliza!
Stand up when you hear your name. Eliza?
Lethe!
John!
Oren.
Platt!
Stand up.
You fit the description given. Why didn't you answer when called?
My name is not Platt. My name is...
Your name is Platt.
Captain, get these niggers to my cart.
I believe I have something
very much your liking in the back room.
Follow me, please.
Yes. Now...
Inspect them at your leisure, but ...
I ask you to pay particular regard to young Ezra right here.
Incredibly solid limbs!
I've never seen anything quite like him.
And this marvelous creature. Can you believe it? Hm?
She'd make a fine living maids, mandam.
So, inspect at your leisure. Take your time.
Help yourself to refreshments.
Gentlemen, what catches your fancy here?
Hm... this boy?
Open your mouth. Open, wide up!
Look in there. Never been sick a day in his life.
And I call particular attention to Martha.
She is an excellent pastry cook.
Ah, Mr. Ford?
Splendid seeing you, sir. What catches your fancy?
This lad, he's very browny.
How much for the ones Platt and Eliza?
Ah, I see...
A thousand for Platt, he is a nigger of considerable talent.
I assure you.
Seven hundred for Eliza.
My fairest price.
- You would accept a note? - Please, sir...
Of course, from you, Mr. Ford.
Please sir, don't divide my family.
Don't take me
- unless you take my children as well. - Eliza, quiet!
You will have the most faithful slave in me.
The most faithful slave that has ever lived,
- but I beg that you do not separate us. - Your price
- for the boy? - Yes, the boy.
- Please! - Stop it!
I will give you something to cry about.
Randall, come forward. Come, come, come.
You see how fit this boy is.
Like ripe fruit.
May I take your stick, for a moment?
Observe this, Randall?
Jump, jump, jump! Run, run, run!
Very good! Higher!
You see this? Very likely he will grow into a fine beast.
Six hundred for the boy,
fair and final.
- Done. - Superb.
A moment, please.
- Mr. Ford? - Please.
- Eliza! - How much for the little girl?
You have no use for her.
One so young will bring you no profit.
No, no, no, no. I cannot sell the girl.
- Please! - There's heaps 'n piles of money to be made for her.
She is a beauty. One of the regular bloods.
None of your thick-lipped, bullet headed,
cotton picking niggers.
- Her child, man. - Please...
For God's sake, are you not sentimental in the least?
My sentimentality extends the length of a coin.
Now do you take this lot, Mr. Ford, or do you pass on them all?
Please, please ...
I will take the ones Platt and Eliza.
So, Eliza and Platt, splendid.
I will not go without my children.
You will not take them from me.
Goddamn! Get her out!
Please! No!
No, no, no...!
Get her out of here! Out! Out! Out!
Nice.
Mr Ford, pleasure.
Did you bring all those niggers?
Two of them?
- You got two? - Mr. Chapin.
This one's cryin'. Why is this one cryin'?
- Separated from her children. - Oh, dear...
- It couldn't be helped. - Poor, poor woman.
- Mr. Chapin. - Yes , sir.
Tomorrow you will take these two up to the mill
and start them workin'.
For now make them adequate,
fix them a meal, and have them rest themselves.
Yes, sir.
C'mon, now. C'mon. Don't dawdle.
Something to eat and some rest;
your children will soon enough be forgotten.
For all of you rotten niggers that don't know,
My name is John Tibeats,
William Ford's chief carpenter.
You will refer to me as Master.
Now, Mister Chapin is the overseer on this plantation,
and you too will refer to him
as Master.
So, clap your hands.
Like this.
Come on. Come on now.
Clap your hands.
Nigger run nigger flew.
Nigger tore his shirt in two.
Run run the pattyroller will get you.
Run nigger run well you better get away
That's right. Like you mean it.
Nigger run, run so fast
Stoved his head in a hornets nest
Run nigger run well the pattyroller will get you
Run nigger run well you better get away
Some folks say a nigger won't steal
I caught three in my corn field
One has a bushel and one has a peck
One had a rope and it was hung around his neck
Run nigger run well the pattyroller will get you
Run nigger run well you better get away
Hey Mr. Pattyroller don't catch me
Catch that nigger behind that tree
Run nigger run well the pattyroller will get you
Run nigger run well you better get away
I am the God of Abraham,
and the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob.
And when the multitude heard this,
they were astonished at his doctrine.
Then one of them, which was a lawyer,
asked him a question, tempting him.
Run nigger run well the pattyroller will get you
Run nigger run well you better get away
The creek is plenty deep enough to sail,
even with a boat full of load.
The distance from the work area to the point on the latter bayou
is several miles by water fewer than land.
It occurs to me that
the expense of the transportation would be materially diminished.
- "Materially diminished?" - If we use the waterway.
Are you an engineer or a nigger?
- Let the man say his piece. - It's a scheme.
Plenty of engineers have schemed similarly.
The passes are too tight.
I reckon them at more than twelve feet at their most narrow.
Wide enough for a tub to traverse,
if a team of niggers cleared it out.
And you know what of transport and terra formin'?
I labored repairing the Champlain canal,
on the section over which
William Van Nortwick was superintendent.
With my earnings I hired several efficient hands to assist me,
and entered into contracts for
the transportation of large rafts of timber
from Lake Champlain to Troy.
I'll admit to being impressed even if you won't.
Collect a team, see what good you can do.
All right, you're good. Clear it up!
One, two, three...
Platt, you are a marvel.
What took you so long?
Thank you, Master Ford.
No, thank you.
- Yeah! - Hi, Model!
Yes, sir!
Platt.
My great thanks, Master Ford.
My thanks to you,
and it is the least of it.
My hope is that it brings us both much joy over the years.
Eliza.
Stop!
Stop your wailing!
You let yourself be overcome by sorrow.
You will drown in it.
Have you stopped crying for your children?
You make no sounds,
but will you ever let them go in your heart?
They are as my flesh...
Then who is distressed?
Do I upset the Master and the Mistress?
Do you care less for my loss
than their well being?
- Master Ford is a decent man. - He is a slaver!
Under the circumstances...
Under the circumstances he is a slaver!
- But you truckle at his boot. - No.
- You luxuriate in his favor. - I survive!
I will not fall into despair!
I will offer up my talents to Master Ford.
I will keep myself hearty until freedom is opportune!
Ford is your opportunity.
Do you think he does not know
that you are more than you suggest?
But he does nothing for you. Nothing.
You are no better than prized livestock.
Call for him. Call,
tell him of your previous circumstances,
and see what it earns you, Solomon.
So, you're settled into your role as Platt, then?
My back is thick with scars from protesting my freedom.
- Do not accuse me. - I accuse you of nothing.
I cannot accuse.
I have done dishonorable things to survive.
And for all of them I have ended up here.
No better than if I had stood up for myself.
God forgive me.
Solomon, let me weep for my children.
Whosoever therefore shall humbles himself as this little child,
the same is greatest in the Kingdom of heaven.
And whoso shall receive one such little child in my name
- receiveth me. - I cannot have that kind of depression about.
But whoso shall offend one of these little ones
it were better for him
that a millstone were hanged about his neck,
and that he were drowned in the depth of the sea.
- Amen. - Amen!
Make them boards flush.
They are, sir.
No, They is no such thing.
As smooth to the touch as a yearling's coat.
Callin' me a liar, boy?
Only a matter of perspective, sir.
From where you stand you may see differently.
But the hands are not mistaken.
I simply ask that you
use all your senses before rendering judgement.
Oh... My...You are a brute.
You are a dog, and no better for followin' instruction.
I'll do as ordered, sir.
Well, then you'll be up at daybreak.
You will procure a keg of nails from Chapin;
and commence to puttin' on clapboards.
Yes, sir .
Make them boards flush.
No, please! Please, Sir!
Where am I going, sir?
Solomon! Solomon!
Solomon!
When I say I had my master's favor,
you understand.
And for nine years
he blessed me with every comfort and luxury in life.
Silks and jewels
and even servants to wait upon us.
Such was our life,
and the life of this beautiful girl I bore for him.
But Master Berry's daughter...
she always looked at me with an unkind nature.
She hated Emily
no matter she and Emily were flesh of flesh.
As Master Berry's health failed,
she gained power in the household and;
Eventually, I was brought to the city on the false pretense
of our free papers being executed.
My poor children.
I thought I told you to commence to puttin' on clapboards.
Yes, master. I am about it.
These have all been replaced.
Didn't I tell yah to get a keg of nails?
And so I did.
So you did.
Goddamn you! I thought you knowed somethin'!
I did as instructed.
If there's something wrong,
it's wrong with your instructions.
You, black bastard!
You...
goddamn...
black bastard!
Strip yer clothes!
Strip!
I will not!
You...
Yew will not live to see another day, nigger!
God, help!
Monster!
Help! Somebody help me! Help!
Help! Somebody!
What is the matter?
- What is the matter? - Master...
Master Tibeats wants to whip me
for using the nails you gave me.
This ain't done by half.
I will have flesh,
and I will have all of it.
Do not stir.
Do not leave the plantation,
for if you run I cannot protect you.
Stay here.
Gentlemen?
Whoever moves that nigger is a dead man.
I am the overseer on this plantation,
William Ford holds a mortgage on Platt.
If you hang him, he will lose his debt.
You have no claim to his life.
As for you two,
if you have any regard for your own safety,
I say, begone!
You got no cause.
Platt is mine, and mine to do with as I please.
If you touch him...
Sam! Get the mule.
Get Master Ford.
Right. Right.
I believe Tibeats is skulkin' about the premises somewhere.
He wants you dead,
and he will have it so.
It's no longer safe for you here.
And I don't believe you will remain passive if Tibeats attacks.
I have transferred my debt to Edwin Epps.
He will take charge of you.
Master Ford?
You must know that I am not a slave.
I cannot hear that.
Before I came to you, I was a freeman.
I am trying to save your life!
And... I have a debt to be mindful of.
And that is to Edwin Epps now.
He is a hard man.
Prides himself on being a "Nigger breaker."
But truthfully, I could find no others who would take you.
You've made a reputation of yourself.
Whatever your circumstances,
you are an exceptional nigger, Platt.
But I fear no good will come of it.
"And that servant
which knew his Lord's will...
which knew his lord's will;
and prepared not himself...
prepared not himself,
neither did according to his will,
shall be beaten with many stripes..."
D'ye hear that?
"Stripes."
That nigger that don't obey his lord,
that's his master,d'ye see?
that 'ere nigger shall be beaten with many stripes.
Now, "many" signifies a great many.
Forty, a hundred,
a hundred and fifty lashes...
That's Scripter!
Pick that cotton.
Move along now!
Come on now!
- Drive dem niggers. - Pick that cotton.
Move along now,
Hear?
What you doing, boy? Come on!
Two hundred forty pounds for Bob.
What yah got for James?
Two hundred ninety five pounds.
Tha's real good, boy. Tha's real good.
One hundred eighty two pounds for Platt.
How much can even an average nigger pick a day?
- Two hundred pounds. - This nigger ain't even average.
Five hundred twelve pounds for Patsey.
Yah men folk got no shame
lettin' Patsey out pick yah?
The day ain't yet come she swung lower than five hundred pounds.
Queen of the fields, she is.
- 138 pounds... - I ain't done, Treach.
Ain't I owed a minute to luxuriate on the work Patsey done?
Yes, sir.
Damned Queen.
Born and bred to the field.
A nigger among niggers,
and God give 'er to me.
A lesson in the rewards of righteous livin'.
All be observant to that.
All!
Now, Treach. Now speak.
One hundred thirty eight pounds for Phebe.
Hit one forty five yesterday. Pull her out.
Two hundred six pounds for George.
How much he pick yesterday?
- Two twenty nine. - Get him out.
Come on, kid.
Come on. Come on, boy, move!
Get up! We dance tonight! Get up!
Get your fiddle, Platt! Get up!
Come on!
Come on, Platt! Come on!
Come on! Where's yah merriment? Move yer feet.
- Sell her! - What's all this?
You will sell the negress!
Sell little Pats?
She pick with more vigor than any other nigger!
- Choose another ta go. - No other.
Sell her!
I will not!
You will remove that black bitch from this property,
or I'll take myself back to Cheneyville.
Back to that hog's trough where I found you?
Do not set yourself up against Patsey, my dear.
'Cause I will rid myself of yah well before I do away with her!
Whatcha looking at?
Damned woman!
I won't have my mood spoiled.
I will not.
Dance!
Dance, I said!
Come on!
Pick it up, Platt. Play that thing, boy!
Platt?
Yes, Mistress.
Can you find your way to Bartholomew's?
I can, ma'am.
This is a list of goods and sundries.
You will take it to be filled and return immediately.
Take your tag.
- Tell Bartholomew to add it to our debt. - Yes, Mistress.
Where yah from, Platt?
- I have told you. - Tell me again.
- Washington. - Who were yah Master?
- Master's name was Freeman. - Was he a learned man?
- I suppose so. - He learn yah ta read?
A word here or there,
but I have no understanding of the written text.
Don't trouble yer self with it.
Same as the rest, Master bought yah to work.
Tha's all.
And any more'll earn yah a hundred lashes.
Come here, boy.
Come on.
- Where are you going, boy? - On my way to
Bartholomew's... sent by Mistress Epps.
You best get there then.
Get there quick.
- Any trouble? - No, ma'am.
No trouble.
Platt Epps, good Sunday morning.
Good morning, Master Shaw.
Master sent me to retrieve Patsey. May I approach?
You may.
Excuse me, Mistress Shaw.
- Nigger Platt. - Patsey, Master wishes you to return.
The Sabbath day. I's free ta roam.
Master sent me running to fetch you,
and said no time should be wasted.
- Drink a tea? - Thank you, Mistress, but I don't dare.
Would you know Massa Epps's consternation
to be any lessened wit your timely return?
Ain't it his constant condition?
Sit. Sit and drink the tea that offered.
What'n be Epps's concern?
I'd rather not say.
L'il gossip on the Sabbath be fine.
All things in moderation.
As you are aware, Master Epps...
is a man of hard countenance.
You know he has ill feeling toward your husband.
He do.
Master Epps has somehow come to believe,
that Master Shaw...
is something of a lothario.
A misguided belief, no doubt.
No doubt... if not born outta truth itself.
I meant no disrespect.
He ain't heard you.
I meant no disrespect to you, Mistress.
Got no cause to worry for my sensibilities.
I ain't felt the end of a lash in 'mo years than I cain recall.
I ain't worked a field, neither.
Where once I served, now I have others servin' me.
The cost to my current existence be Massa Shaw..
broadcasting his affections and
me enjoyin' the pantomime of his fidelity.
If that what keep me from the cotton pickin' niggers,
that what it be.
A small and reasonable price to be paid 'fo sure.
I knowed what it like
to be the object of Massa's predilections and peculiarities.
A lusty visit in the night,
or a visitation with the whip.
Take comfort, Patsey;
Good Lord will manage Epps.
In His own time the Good Lord will manage dem all.
The curse of the pharaohs
were a poor example of all that wait 'fo the plantation class.
This is nice.
Patsey?
- Patsey! - Do not look in his direction. Continue on.
- Patsey! - Found her, Master,
and brought her back just as instructed.
What'd you jus now tell her?
What'd you say to Pats?
No words were spoken. None of consequence.
Lie! Damned liar!
Saw you talkin' with 'er.
Tell me!
I cannot speak of what did not occur.
- I'll cut your black throat. - Master...
You come here!
- Master, I brought... - I said come here!
I brought her back, just like you ...
- Come here! - Come on, let's go!
I got her, just as instructed.
Stay away from Pats, boy!
It's the Lord's day.
Ain't nothin' Christian in us carryin' on like this.
I concede to yah,
but in the name of valor,
help yer master to his feet.
What's the fuss?
Master Epps believed Patsey and me to be in conversation
when we were not.
I tried to explain, but it's led to all this.
What is it?
Ya can't remain the Sabbath without her under your eye?
- Hold on... - Ya are a no-account bastard.
A filthy, godless heathen.
My bed is too holy for yah ta share.
- Wha's he been tellin' yah? - Of yer misbegotten ways.
And he would know what of anythin'?
I ain't even spoken with him today.
Yah lyin' nigger, Platt.
Have I?
There. There's all the truth he got.
Damned nigger.
Patsey?
A moment from the dancing.
Come sample what I baked for y'all.
- Thank you, Mistress! - Thank you, Mistress!
- Thank you, Mistress. - There'll be none for you, Patsey.
Yah see that?
Yah see that look of insolence she give me?
Seen nothin' but her turn away.
Are you blind or ignorant?
It was hot, hateful scorn.
It filled that black face.
Yah tell me yah did'n see it, then yah choose not to look,
or yah sayin' I lie.
Whatever it was, it passed.
Is that how yah are with the niggers?
Lettin' every ill thought fester inside 'em.
Look at them.
They foul with it;
They foul with their hate.
You let it be, it's gonna come back to us in the dark a night.
Yah want that?
Yah want them black animals
leave us gut like pigs in our own sleep?
No...
You are manless.
A damned eunuch if ever there was.
And if yah won't stand for me,
I'd pray you'd at least be a credit to yer own kind,
and beat every foul thought from 'em.
Beat it from 'em!
Eat!
Fill yourselves.
And then we dance.
I said, eat!
Platt...
Platt, you awake?
I am.
I have a request.
An act of kindness.
I secreted it from the Mistress.
- Return it! - It yours, Platt.
For what cause?
All I ask is end my life.
Take my body to the margin of the swamp.
Take me by the throat. Hold me low in the water
until I's still 'n without life.
Bury me in a lonely place of dyin'.
I will do no such thing.
The gory detail with which you speak...
I thought on it long and hard.
It is melancholia,
nothing more.
How can you fall into such despair?
How can you not know?
I ain't got no comfort in this life.
If I cain't buy mercy from yah, I'll beg it.
There are others.
Beg them.
- I'm begging you! - Why?
Why would you consign me
to damnation with such an un-Godly request?
There is God here!
God is merciful,
and He forgive merciful acts.
Won't be no hell for you.
Do it.
Do what I ain't got the strength ta do myself.
It is a plague.
- It's cotton worm. - It's a plague! It's damn Biblical.
Two seasons God don't sent a plague to smite me.
What I done that God hate me so?
It's that Godless lot.
They brought this on me.
I bring 'em God's word, and heathens they are,
they brought me God's scorn.
Damn you!
Damn all, you all!
- Judge? - Mr. Epps.
I am deeply sadden to hear about your misfortune.
?
Listen up.
Yer Judge Turner's for the season.
More if need be,
until my crop return.
Yah'll bring no disrespect to me,
and yah'll bring no biblical plagues to him. You hear?
Or I'll take all your skin.
Get out.
Get off the porch! You ain't supposed to be on the porch.
Get off the porch!
Platt is it?
- Yes , sir. - Have you cultivated cane previously?
- No, sir. I am not. - It comes to you quite naturally.
- Are you educated? - No, sir.
Niggers are hired to work, not read or write.
- You play the fiddle? - Yes , sir.
Yes, I do.
Willard Yarney, a planter up the bayou,
celebrates his anniversary in a three week's time.
I will hold out your name to him.
What you earn is yours to keep.
Yes, sir.
Mind yourself, Platt.
Joyous day.
Dark times is behind us.
Clean livin' 'n prayer done lifted the plague.
As thick 'n white as New England snow.
'N now my niggers is returned to me.
Heard Judge Turner gave you favor.
Oh, did you beguile him, Platt,
with your slick nigger ways?
Well, yah won't stand idle, boy.
Not on my land.
Much work to do.
Days of old long since, eh?
Joyous! Joyous indeed!
Let's go find something sweet for you. Hmm?
- Candy. - Candy?
- George? - One hundred and eighty pounds.
- Patsey? - Five hundred twenty pounds for Patsey.
Tha's my girl. Don't never let me down.
- Platt? - One hundred sixty pounds.
Armsby?
Sixty four pounds.
A good days labor would average two hundred pounds.
Yes, sir.
I'm sure in time y'll develope as a picker,
but it takes effort, boy.
- Put some damn effort into it. - Yes, sir.
Take 'em out. Get to whippin'.
It's a tragedy.
How does such come to pass?
Working a field and picking cotton like a lowly hand.
I'm of a damn sight better station.
I've worked as an overseer, you know.
- I did not know, sir. - Not "Sir."
Just Armsby.
Not owed more than any other in the field.
How did you arrive at such a place, if I may ask?
Ask. It's just conversation.
I became a little too dependant on the whisky,
a little too undependable on the job.
Before you say I'm just a sorry drunkard,
let me state my case:
As reliable employment as overseeing is,
it's no easy chore on the spirit.
I say no man of conscious;
can take the lash to another human day in and day out
without shredding at his own self.
Takes him to a place...
where he either makes excuses within his mind to be unaffected...
or finds some way to trample his guilty sensations.
Well, I trampled,
with frequency.
I gave in to tales of wealth and prosperity,
but such profitable outcomes
are reserved for the plantation masters.
It's the lot of the rest of us to serve.
Now, all I want is to earn a decent wage
and get myself home.
The proceeds of my fiddling performances.
Just a few picayunes,
but all I have in the world.
I promise them to you if you will do me the favor I require.
But I beg you not to expose me if you cannot grant the request.
What...
- What is it that you ask? - First, your word, sir.
On my honor.
It is a simple enough request.
I only ask you to post a letter
at the post office in Marksville
and that you keep the action an inviolable secret forever.
A patron is what I require, sir.
I'll do it.
And I will accept whatever payment is offered.
To assist you, I put my own self at risk.
I will do so,
but fair compensation is all I ask.
Draw up your letter.
We will meet again. In two days?
In two days.
Thank you.
Well, boy.
I understand I've got a learned nigger
that writes letters...
and tries to get white fellows to mail 'em.
Well, Armsby tol' me today
the devil was among my niggers.
that I have one that needed watchin'
or he would run away.
When I asked him why
he said you come over to him,
and waked him up in the middle of the night,
and wanted him to carry a letter
to Marksville.
What yah got to say to that?
There is no truth to it.
You say.
How could I write a letter without ink or paper?
Who am I going to write to?
I got no friends living as I know of.
That Armsby...
That Armsby is a lying drunken fellow.
Didn't he want you to hire him as an overseer?
That's it.
He wants to make you believe we're all going to run away
so you'll hire him an overseer.
He believes you are soft soap,
and he's given to such talk,
made this story out of whole cloth,
because he wants the situation.
It's all a lie, master.
It's all a lie.
I'll be damned.
Were he not free and white, Platt.
Were he not free and white.
Edward? Give him water!
Get up.
Nigger, get up.
What are you looking at, boy?
Keep picking, boy.
I just want to say something
'bout Uncle Abram.
He was a good man
and he always looked out for us, ever since we were little.
God love him.
God bless him. God keep him.
Amen.
Wait till the end.
Hey, Bass?
No, no, no...
No shame in taking respite from the heat,
drink, shade.
It's ungodly for travelers. Hearty, or otherwise.
- What's funny ? - Epps, I'm here to finish the work at hand.
As requested and as paid for.
Something rubs you wrongly.
I offer you the opportunity to speak off.
Well. You ask plainly, so I will tell you plainly.
What amused me just then, was...
your concern for my well being in this heat,
when quite frankly,
the conditions of your labours...
- The condition of my labour? - It is hard!
- What the hell? - It's all wrong. All wrong, Mr. Epps.
They ain't hired to help.
They are my property.
- You say that with pride. - I say it as fact.
This conversation concerns what is fact and what's not.
Then it must be said.
That there is no justice, or righteousness in this slavery.
But you do open up a interesting question.
What right have you to your niggers
- when you come down to the point? - What right?
I bought them, I paid for them.
Of course you did,
and the law say's you have the right to hold a nigger.
But begging the laws pardon, it lies.
Suppose they pass the law, take away your liberty,
making you a slave.
- Suppose. - That ain't a supposable case.
Laws change, Epps. Universal truths though are constant.
It is a fact, a plain and simple fact
that what is true and right is true and right for all.
White and black alike.
Yah compare me to a nigger, Bass?
I am only asking, in the eye's of God, what is the difference?
Yah might as well ask
what the difference is between a white man and a baboon.
Now, I've seen one of them critters in Orleans
that knowed just as much as any nigger I got.
Listen, Epps... These niggers are human beings.
If they are allowed to claim no higher than brute animals,
you and men like you will have to answer for it.
There's an ill, Mr. Epps,
a fearful ill, resting upon this nation,
and there will be a day of reckoning yet.
You like to hear yourself talk, Bass,
better than any man I know of.
Yah argue that black was white, or white black.
If anybody contradict you,
a fine supposition if yah lived among Yankees in New England.
But yah don't.
You most assuredly do not.
I know it's somewhere in there!
Patsey!
Pats!
Where is she?
Where is Pats?
Where is she? Tell me, where is she?
Where is she? Where is Pats? Where is she?
Whatcha standing there for?
- We know nothin' of her, massa. - Know none of what?
- We know nothin' of her. - Of what?
- Where did she go? - I do not know.
- She run off, ain't she? - I know nothing.
She ran off! Where is she?
?
- You know! You know! You know! - No, no, no...
No I don't.
You miserable black dogs stand like the deef and dumb.
Speak!
She's gone...
My Pats is gone.
Run off. Run off, did you?
- Massa Epps... - You miserable wench! Where have you been?
- I've been nowhere. - Lies to your misdeeds!
The Sabbath day, massa. I took me a walk to commune with the Lord.
Bring the Lord into yer deceptions?
Yah comin' from Shaw's plantation, weren't yah?
- No. - Now yah speak?
Now that yah want to add to her lies yah find yer tongue!
I went to Massa Shaw's plantation!
- You admit it? - Yes.
Freely. And you know why?
I got this from Mistress Shaw.
Mistress Epps won't even grant me no soap ta clean with.
I stink so much I make myself gag.
Five hundred pounds of cotton day in, day out!
More than any man here.
And for that I will be clean;
that's all I ask.
Dis here what I went to Shaw's 'fo.
- Liar! - Lord knows it all!
- You Liar! - And you blind wit yer own covetousness.
I don't lie, Massa.
If you kill me, I'll stick to that.
Yeah, I'll set you down.
I'll learn you to go to Shaw's.
Treach!
Go fetch some line.
Edward?
Strip her. Strike her bare 'n lash her to the post.
No!
Yah done this to yourself, Pats!
Do it!
Strike the life from her.
Beat her.
Give her the whip. Give it all to her!
Platt, you come here and you beat her now!
Platt!
Come here!
I'd rather it you, Platt.
Strike her.
He pantomimes.
There ain't barely a welt on her.
That's what your niggers make of yah;
a fool fer the takin'.
Strike her, Platt! Strike her.
Yah will strike her.
Yah will strike her until her flesh is rent...
and meat and blood flow equal,
or I will kill every nigger in my sight!
Do you understand me? Strike her!
Strike her!
Until I say no more! I ain't said nothing!
Give me the whip!
Give it!
Get up!
Thou devil!
Sooner or later,
somewhere in the course of eternal justice
thou shalt answer for this sin!
Sin? There is no sin.
A man does how he pleases with his property.
At the moment, Platt, I am of great pleasure.
You be goddamn careful
I don't want to come lightenin' my mood no further.
Master Bass,
I want to ask you what part of the country you come from?
No part of this land.
Originate from Canada.
Now guess where that is.
Oh, I know where Canada is.
I have been there myself.
Montreal and
Kingston and Queenston and a great many places.
Well traveled for a slave.
How came you here?
Master Bass,
if justice had been done I never would have been here.
How's this?
Tell me all.
I am afraid to tell you.
Every word you speak is a profound secret.
Your story,
it is amazing, and in no good way.
Do you believe, sir,
in justice as you have said?
I do.
That slavery is an evil that should befall none?
- I believe so. - If you truly do,
then, I ask...
I beg...
that you write my friends in the north,
acquainting them with my situation,
and beseeching them to forward
free papers.
It would be...
an unspeakable happiness,
to see my wife
and my family again.
I've traveled this country for the best part of twenty years.
My freedom is everything.
The fact that I can walk out of here tomorrow
brings me great pleasure.
My life doesn't mean much to anyone,
but seems yours might mean a lot to a whole lot of people.
But what you ask me,
Sir, scares me.
And I must say, I am afraid.
Not just for you, but for me.
I will write your letter, sir,
and if it brings you your freedom,
it will be more than a pleasure,
it will be my duty.
Now, would you kindly hand me those shingles?
Platt? Where is the boy called Platt?
Come here, boy.
Your name is Platt, is it?
Yes, sir.
Do you know that man?
Mr. Parker?
Say again?
That man received a letter compiling many accusations.
You look me in the eye,
and on your life you answer me truthfully:
have you any other name than Platt?
- Solomon Northup is my name. - Sheriff, what's all this?
- It's official business. - My nigga, my business.
Your business waits.
- Tell me of your family. - Platt.
I have a wife and two children.
- What the hell? - What were your children's names?
- Margaret and Alonzo. - And your wife's name before her marriage?
Anne Hampton. I am who I say.
Where are you going, Platt?
- Who authorized you to interfere with my property? - My authority.
Platt, you come back here! Platt!
You come back here, boy!
You will unhand him. Platt is my nigger!
- He is Mr. Solomon Northup! - You say,
you come here, unfamiliar to me and make claims.
We got no doubts. The man is Solomon Northup.
To hell he is! He's my nigger, and I'll fight you for him!
As is your right.
As it will be my pleasure to bankrupt you in the courts.
Your decision. Unhand him!
I know you had some hand in this plan.
I'm gonna get to the bottom of it.
It ain't no mine.
I paid good money for this nigga!
The courthouse got papers to prove it!
And we got papers proving he is free!
I own you! You belong to me! You hear me with that?
Unhand him!
The court will start to cast you back by sundown!
- Platt! - Get my horse, Treach.
Get away from him, Pats!
- I'll be seeing you real soon. - Solomon, we need to make haste.
- No. - Solomon!
I apologize
for my appearance.
But I have had
a difficult time
these past several years.
Margaret?
Alonzo?
Who is this?
He's my husband.
Husband.
It is very good to meet you, sir.
We have much acquainting to do.
Yes, sir.
And this
is your grandson.
Solomon Northup Staunton.
Solomon.
Forgive me.
There is nothing to forgive.